Finding Aid for the Edward Gordon Craig Papers LSC.1006
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Section Eight: Designs
  - Original Prints: Bookplates Designed and Printed by Gordon Craig
    - Lindsay-1900. [Lindsay Jardine]., (Woodcut, 4.5 × 4.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - AL. [Aimée Lowther]., (Woodcut, 7 × 9 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - MP. [Margaret Palgrave]., (Woodcut, 8 × 6.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Roche-1900. [C.E. Roche]., (Woodcut, 7.5 × 6.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - This book belongs to William Winter., (Woodcut, 6.5 × 7.5 cm. 3 copies, one colored) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - NFD. [N.F. Dryhurst]., 1901.; (Woodcut, 13 × 10 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - LB3. [Louis Buddy III]., (Woodcut, 25.5 × 20.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Nina. [Lady Corbet]., (Woodcut, 9 × 5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - GC-1901. [Gordon Craig]., (Woodcut, 9 × 6.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - AR. [Lady Ridley]., (Woodcut, 13 × 9 cm. 2 copies, one colored) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Ex libris CBP. [Cora Brown Potter]., (Woodcut, 11.5 × 9 cm., colored) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - JBR. [Jutta Bell Ranski], (Woodcut, 7.5 × 4 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - SG. Owner not identified., 1902.; (Woodcut, 4 × 4 cm., colored and mounted, initialed and dated in ink) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Sidney Painter., 1903.; (Woodcut, 10 × 9 cm., colored) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - AS. Owner not identified., 1904.; (Woodcut, 4.5 × 4 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled. [Roman soldier; bookplate designed for Jan de Vos]., 1906.; (Woodcut, 13 × 10 cm., signed in pencil) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - D. Owner not identified., 1910.; (Woodcut, 15 × 13 cm., initialed and dated in pencil, copy 22 of 150) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - P. Elsewhere dated 1912 [G.W. Plank]., (Woodcut, 18 × 13 cm., initialed and dated in pencil, copy 20 of 50) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Ex libris WG. [W.F. Gable]., 1912.; (Woodcut, 2 proofs on one 18 × 13 cm. sheet) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - G. Another proof. Same as above., (Woodcut) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled sketches for bookplate., 1917.; (9.5 × 15.5 cm. and 7.5 × 10 cm., 2 items, pen and ink on two sheets) (Box 15, Folder 35)
      Sketches of designs for bookplate for Max Beerbohm.
    - Ex libris Rosie-1926. [Rosie Craig]., (Woodcut, 7.5 × 4.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
      From design of 1898.
    - d. Owner not identified., 1929.; (Woodcut, 7.5 × 6.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled., 1931.; (Woodcut, 14 × 10 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
      Noted in pencil: 4 artist's proofs. no.1 Second state. 1931. M from P. 1935.
    - ER. Owner not identified., n.d.; (Woodcut, 11.5 × 9 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled. Owner not identified., (Woodcut, 13 × 10 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled. Owner not identified., n.d.; (Woodcut, 8 × 6.5 cm.) (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled. Owner not identified., (Woodcut, 13 × 18 cm., 2 copies) (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Original Prints: Stationery from Woodcuts Designed by Gordon Craig
    - Personal stationery for Ellen Terry., circa 1900.; (18 × 11.5 cm., 1 item) (Box 15, Folder 36)
      Vine Cottage, Kingston Vale--ET with grape cluster.
    - Personal stationery., (18 × 11.5 cm., 1 item) (Box 15, Folder 36)
      Tower Cottage, Winchelsea, Sussex with scene.
    - Business receipts for Edith Craig & Company., (16.5 × 19 cm., 1 item) (Box 15, Folder 36)
      Debtor to Edith Craig & Company...
    - Greeting card., 1913.; (10 × 13 cm., 1 item) (Box 15, Folder 36)
      With every good wish, Elena & Gordon Craig, 1913. Initialed and dated in cut.
  - Original Prints: Reproductions
    - Reproductions of original prints by Gordon Craig. v.p., v.d.; (10 items) (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Original Prints: Wood Blocks Used in the Production of Printed Material
    - The Page. Wood and zinc printing blocks used in the publication of the periodical published by Craig, The Page. n.p., circa 1900.; (4 items) (Box 16)
    - Souvenir of Acis and Galatea. Wood and zinc block used in the publication of the program for the play produced by Gordon Craig. n.p., circa 1902.; (1 item) (Box 16)
    - Gordon Craig's Book of Penny Toys. Wood and zinc printing blocks used in the publication of the book. n.p., circa 1899.; (38 items) (Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
    - The Cranach Press Hamlet with illustrations by Gordon Craig. Wood and metal blocks used in the publication of this edition: Weimer, Gedruck and Aufder Cranach Presse, n.p., 1928. n.d. (Box 20, Box 21)
  - Original Prints: Etched Plates Designed by Gordon Craig
    - Etched plates used in the production of Scene, 1923. (Box 22)
      Were made to illustrate Craig's concept of arrested motion in scenic development. During progressive stages in the etchings process, the illusion of greater light appeared to gradually reveal the scene; a process similar to that achieved by Craig's use of materials in set design which provided the illusion of ephemeral scenes.
      - Original Prints: Etched Plates for Scene, (1923)
        - Etching no.1--small opening., 1907.; (Metal plate, etched, 10.5 × 8.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 1)
          Plate no.1 in Scene.
        - Little tomb., 1907.; (Copper plate, etched, 10.5 × 17 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 2)
          Plate no.2 in Scene.
        - Masked figure., 1907.; (Metal plate, etched, 11 × 16.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 3)
          Plate no.6 in Scene.
        - Uber-marionette., 1907.; (Metal plate, etched, 16.5 × 10.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Plate no.8 in Scene.
        - French revolution., 1907.; (Metal plate, etched, 16.75 × 16 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 5)
          Plate no.10 in Scene.
        - Light - Etching no._____., 1907.; (Copper plate, etched, 21 × 16.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 6)
          Plate no.13 in Scene.
        - Descending into tomb., 1907.; (Copper plate, etched, 21 × 16.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 7)
          Plate no.15 in Scene.
        - Childe Roland., 1907.; (Copper plate, etched, 10.5 × 17 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 8)
          Plate no.19 in Scene.
    - Original Prints: Etched Plates for Hamlet
      - Claudius., circa 1910.; (Copper plate, etched, 9.5 × 12 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Hamlet play-scene -- like wood -- engraving -- Extra., circa 1910.; (Copper plate, etched, 11 × 10.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - Hamlet -- Extra., circa 1910.; (Copper plate, etched, 17 × 10.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Original Prints: Miscellaneous Etched Plates
      - Girl with long arm -- zinc plate -- extra., n.d.; (Zinc plate, etched, 18.75 × 10.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - Ponte Vecchio., n.d.; (Copper plate, etched, 8.5 × 10.5 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Bookplate., n.d.; (Metal plate, etched, 5 × 3 cm.) (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Designs: Toy Theatres
    - Pollock toy theatre. Published by B. Pollock. Hoxton, circa 1870.; OVERSIZE ITEM L; (Hand-colored cardboard and wood, stage and scenery 45 × 37.5 × 43 cm. assembled)
      Representing characters and scenes from Dickens' Oliver Twist.
      Bookplate (GC-1898) on reverse of curtain.
      (On display in Smith Room, Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, UCLA.)
    - Miscellaneous hand-colored cardboard and wood characters and scenes for toy theatres. n.p. (Box 23, Box 24)
      - Skelt's characters and scenes for The Forty Thieves, M. & M. Skelt. London
      - Skelt's characters and scenes for The Miller's Maid, M. & M. Skelt. London
      - Pollock's characters and scenes for The Miller and His Men, B. Pollock. Hoxton
      - Redington's new drop scene of the standard theatre. n.p.
  - Designs: Model Stages
    - Macbeth Model stage constructed by Gordon Craig, circa 1908.; OVERSIZE ITEM M; (Damaged; in fragmented pieces) (Box 30, 32)
    - Macbeth Model stages constructed by Gordon Craig, circa 1910.; OVERSIZE ITEMS N-O; (2 stages, each in large wooden shipping crate. Cardboard, paper and wood construction. Approximately 80 × 60 × 40 cm. when assembled) (Box 33, Box 34)
      Hand-colored stage and scene.
    - How Doth the City Sit Solitary. n.p., circa 1910.; OVERSIZE ITEM P; (Approximately 25 × 25 × 25 cm.) (Box 27)
      Model stage constructed by Gordon Craig for his son, E.A. Craig.
      A rendering of Craig's 1907 woodcut, How Doth the City Sit Solitary.
    - Models of scenery and furnishings, fragments of model stages, circa 1913.; OVERSIZE ITEM Q (Box 31)
      Includes sections of stage for Bach's Passion of St. Matthew and some work of Craig's students at 'The School for the Art of the Theatre,' Florence.
  - Designs: Puppets and Marionettes
    Biographical/Historical note
    Gordon Craig's interest in marionettes can be traced back as far as 1905, with the publication of The Art of the Theatre. (London: Foulis, 1905) In 1907, Craig wrote a critical review of acting titled The Actor and the über-marionette, which was published in the second issue of The Mask in April, 1908. Gordon Craig's plays for puppets included The Gordian Knot, Mr. Fish and Mrs. Bones, The Tune the Old Cow Died of, and The Three Men of Gorham, which were published in his journal, The Marionette, in 1918 and issued separately in limited editions in the same year. He also wrote a version of Romeo and Juliet for marionettes which was issued only in a limited edition, also in 1918.
    - Hand-puppets and marionettes. Florence, circa 1910.; (18 figures, Wood, metal and plaster-bodied figures of varying size; dressed in cloth, paper and metal) (Box 25)
    - Wooden figure. n.p., n.d.; (1 item. 18 cm. in height, hand-carved) (Box 25)
    - Javanese marionettes, 18th century.; OVERSIZE ITEM R; (50 cm. in height, 3 items) (Box 29)
      Movable figures of hand-colored buffalo hide, used in the Wayang Purwa (shadow theatre) of Java.
    - Javanese marionette, 18th century.; OVERSIZE ITEM S; (75 cm. in height, 1 item) (Box 29)
      Movable figure of hand-colored buffalo hide, used in the Wayang Purwa (shadow theatre) of Java.
    - Figure of African holding tray. n.p., n.d.; OVERSIZE ITEM T; (50 cm. in height, in box) (Box 29)
      Henry Irving's visiting card holder.
      (missing)
- Section Nine: Bibliography
  - Fletcher, Ifan Kyrle and Arnold Rood. Edward Gordon Craig: a bibliography. London: The Society for Theatre Research, 1967. (Box 1)
    Annotated by holdings of the Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, UCLA.